Never forget why you are the church.
Romans chapter 12.
We're going to be in, we've
been in verse 12, but we're going to continue right along, looking
at each command given to us regarding our relationship with others.
Remember, we're looking at the impact of the gospel and how the gospel changes our lives.
And so it changed our lives regarding how we
interact with each other and how we coordinate
and really conduct our relationships with each other.
Now, we have taken them one by one because there is so much truth packed in each one.
The last several weeks, we went over specifically Romans 12, verse 12.
It says this, rejoicing and hope, patient and tribulation, continuing instant in prayer.
In other words, these are commandments that we are given.
We are to be rejoicing in hope, patient in tribulation, continuing instant in prayer.
My prayer for us as a church is that we face the pressures.
We face the tribulations.
We face the times of need not only together, but in a biblical God honoring way.
And the good part is that we know how to do it because he tells us how to do so.
So we're gonna roll right along to the next command in Romans 12, verse 13.
And if you're there in verse 13 of Romans 12, say, read.
It says this distributing to the necessity of saints, given to hospitality.
Distributing to the necessity of saints, given
to hospitality, if you want a title this morning,
you can have one, it is called eternal contributions.
Eternal contributions.
Let's pray.
Father, I thank you, Lord, for this day.
I thank you just for the, God, just a great time we're having in you, God, and for you and through you, God.
And so, Lord, I pray, God, that those have ears to hear me, they hear?
God, give me power and clarity and boldness to preach the word.
God, I pray that I don't preach opinion, but I preach your word,
God, I pray, Lord, that as we gather, God, that we receive the word and gladness.
And God, I just pray, Lord, you continue to work amongst us.
And God, if there's someone here who does not know your son Jesus is Lord and Savior, God, I pray today.
through them understanding that Jesus lived, died, and rose again so that they could be saved.
God, I pray that they call upon his name this morning.
God, we thank me, love us, in Jesus name, and everybody said?
Amen.
The command we are given here is that we are to be distributing to the necessity of the saints.
This can be more clearly read, honestly, as contributing to the necessity of the saints.
So we know the command, but what does it even mean to contribute to the necessity of saying?
Well, here's where the rubber meets the road regarding our relationships to others.
Up until now, the commands have been primarily attitude related.
The only physical actions commanded
have been really to serve and to pray, but even
then you can do that kind of sort of on your own prayer wise at least.
But everything else speaks of a biblical attitude adjustment.
And that being said, there is an important truth here.
When you adjust your attitude towards God, hear me, godly actions will follow.
When you adjust your attitude towards God, when your heart posture is fixed to Christ, then godly actions will follow.
Do not tell me that you have a biblical attitude adjustment if you're still living in sin.
Don't tell me that you have a biblical attitude adjustment
when you're still mean and sour to everybody that you come across.
Listen, when you have a biblical attitude
adjustment like we've talked about the last several weeks, it is
going to come out in the way that you treat others the way that you act the way that you do.
That's what happens with the attitude adjustment.
This command on verse 13, we're in verse 13 speaks of the physical action of sharing material possessions with those in need.
That word distributing in the Greek literally means to share.
But it also brings the meaning of to do together.
Participate in.
Can I tell you it's easy?
We've talked about this already this morning.
It's easy to tell someone you'll pray for them.
It's easy to be happy in church while serving the Lord.
It's easy to serve with passion, our risen savior.
By the way, it should be.
Amen.
If it's not, then you need a biblical attitude adjustment.
It may not be easy to rejoice in the difficult times or persevere through the pressures of life.
But it can still be done really without the involvement of others,
although not as successfully because God says we're supposed to be living this life together.
But here, these commandments, there's no hiding.
There's no pretending.
There's no way to successfully fake being a member of a church and not contributing.
This command came naturally to the church.
What do we see in the early church in Jerusalem?
Next chapter 2, verse 44 through 45, in the
description of what they were doing, and it says, and all those who had
believed were together and had all things in common.
And they began selling their property in possessions and were sharing them withal as anyone might have need.
If you go to Acts chapter 4, verse 32, it says, in the congregation
of those who believe, we're of one heart and soul, and
not one of them claim that anything belonging to him was his
own, but all things were common property to them.
If you look in just a few verses later, in Acts 4,
34 through 37, for there was not a needy person among them.
For all who are owners of land or houses would sell them and bring
their proceeds to the sales and lay them at the apostles'
feet, and they would be distributed to each as any had need.
And we get an example of this.
Now, Joseph, a Levi of Cyprian birth, who was also called
Barnabas by the apostles, which translated means
son of encouragement, and who owned a tract of land,
sold it, and brought the money and laid it at the apostles' feet.
Now, I know what you're thinking right here,
right now, and the enemy tried to get me this week because
I'm preparing this, and I know that anytime we talk about money in the church,
People get all tense and get all angry and get all red faced about it.
Can I tell you something?
When it came to the early church, no one shied away about the topic of money.
Today, we want to come up with every possible loophole and excuse
on why we don't have to give or why we don't have to tithe.
Well, let's look at this.
Let's look at that and do all these logistics, semantics and stuff or partake in special offerings.
Listen, this was not an issue for the early believers.
Why?
Because when you contribute to the needs of the saints, the
result is a unity that bears evident fruit to those involved and those who see.
This practice does not end in Acts chapter 2.
The church in Antioch clearly lived out this command.
In Acts chapter 11, verse 27 through 30.
It says this, and in these days came prophets from Jerusalem unto Antioch.
And there stood up one of them named Agabus, and signified
by the Spirit that there should be a great dearth throughout all the world,
which came to pass in the days of Claudius Caesar.
Then the disciples, every man according to his ability,
determined to send relief unto the brethren was dwelt in Judea, which also they did, and sent it to the elders by the hand of Barnabas and Saul.
What we have here is a man named Agabus, a prophet
of God, telling a church in Antioch, there was a coming, a great dirt.
That means that there was a famine coming, that would create a taste or a experience of prolonged hunger.
In other words, food was about to run out.
People are about to be in need.
Now, notice how to disciples.
responded.
I like how the NASB 95 words this.
It says this.
And in the proportion that any of the disciples had means,
each of them determined to send a contribution for the relief of the brethren living in Judea.
And this they did.
sending it in charge of Barnabas and Saul to the elders.
There's a couple of pointers we can receive from these believers in Antioch.
First, notice they were determined to contribute.
They were determined to contribute nowhere in this account.
They had to be constant request.
There was not an 8 week series on giving, like many churches do.
There was no panel discussion on why we needed this money.
They were simply a man of God that spoke the word of God
and said, hey, listen, there's a famine coming, and there's going to be a need.
And when they heard it, they determined that they would help send relief.
for that need.
Listen to me, church.
There was a need, and that was responded with determination.
They did not do this out of manipulation or coercion, but rather out of a loving obligation.
We want to take the obligation out of giving today in the modern church.
When I say, well, no preacher's going to tell me to give.
No preacher's going to tell me to participate.
No preacher's going to tell me to do this or do that.
I need you to just understand something.
When God commands something.
There is a natural obligation for those who have received his grace to follow that command.
In the words of Jesus, he says this, if ye love me, keep my commandments.
By the way, as a matter of fact, in 1st John, it talks about, hey, hey,
listen, to know someone who is loving Jesus and
walking with Jesus is not just that they keep his commandments, but they're not burdensome for them.
When we start complaining about serving the king of kings and Lord or
Lords, the risen savior, Jesus Christ, there's something wrong.
Are y'all with me this morning?
I knew 25% of you would turn me off right from the get go.
I did.
But you know what?
Just to be transparent with you.
I know that and again, I've
put this together and I've studied, I've done all the things.
But in the back of my mind, I'm thinking, man, we're
having so many visitors come and go and all the things and and
you know that when you preach on giving, you know that people don't receive it well.
Can I tell you something?
In case you're wondering why I'm preaching this this morning, it's the next verse.
Amen?
Come on, now.
Last week we went over verse 12.
And this week we were going over verse 13.
I will not apologize for God's word.
Amen?
But notice how they looked at his offering.
Acts 11, verse 29, and in the proportion that any of the disciples had
means, each of them determined to send a contribution.
Why?
For the relief of the brethren living in Judea.
When we think of relief, we think of making a situation easier.
Right?
The definition of relief per the dictionary is as follows.
A good relaxed feeling when pain, worry, or trouble ends.
Have you ever felt the relief of something you think was going to happen,
then you realize it wasn't going to happen, or maybe you've had a pain
somewhere in your body, then you get relief, and that's what we see as relief.
We can all relate to certain times in our life where we have experienced
relief in those exact 3 things, pain, worry, and trouble.
As a matter of fact, you know, we give money
to the Tennessee Baptist Mission Board and there's a big group that
they that they league called disaster relief, right?
When people go to other places, whether close or
far and help those who have experienced disaster.
If you remember the tornado in 2020, right?
a lot of disaster relief to go and help those who
could really not help themselves in that time.
But look again, so we don't forget what we're talking about here in verse 29
And in the proportion that any of the disciples had means, each of
them determined to send a contribution for the relief of the brethren living in Judea.
The word relief in the Greek literally means ministry and service.
Ministry, think about that for a second.
refers to a ministry of service, either waiting on others or a ministry in the church.
There was no confusion or mistake here.
See, this loving obligation of contributing to
the needs of the saints was not simply for the relief of trouble
in Jerusalem, but it was a primary function and ministry of the church in Antioch.
In other words, when they saw there was a need, they were determined to send relief.
It was a ministry.
It wasn't just the one and done situation.
It was the service that they had as a local body of believers.
This brings to the truth that we need to understand about with any doubts.
A thriving church is a giving church.
A church that doesn't have to be concerned about money as a church that can make immediate and lasting impact.
This brings us to the next pointer that we get from the believers in Antioch.
They were not only determined to send relief.
Look again at the next at the text.
I love this in verse 30. and they did this.
In other words, and this they did, sending in charge of Barnabas and Saul to the elders.
Let me put it in turns that we understand.
So they did it.
They were determined to send relief, therefore they did so.
Are y'all missing that this morning?
Hello, someone say amen to me.
They were determined to send relief and they did so.
Church, when you become determined to minister to others.
The red tape that we like to put on things becomes less sticky.
See, we have all these policies and procedures.
Nowhere is mention of a business meeting.
Nowhere is mention of a committee being formed.
Nowhere is mention of a tabling or postponing of the
offering to further investigate the need and seeing if we're being, you know, right in this.
No, no, no.
I'm not saying that we should not conduct business in a professional and careful way.
Listen, committees are not evil.
They are much of the time very useful and necessary.
A budget is needed.
Part of the way of contributing to the saints today is
being a good steward of the contributions that takes time, and that takes structure.
So I'm not trying to say that we don't have that.
What I'm trying to say is this.
None of these procedures should ever get in the way of
the active fluid spirit led ministry at Cedar Grove Baptist Church.
In other words, policy and procedures are there to protect the church not to stop the church.
If we follow the pattern in tone of these commandments in Romans 12.
We will find that these commandments are not just to the church as a whole, but to the individual believer.
We have to remember that the church, even a local church is a collection
of like-minded believers and followers of Jesus Christ.
Now, why is this important to remember?
Because according to scripture, participation is not optional.
To sit back and let everyone else be devoted to each other, serve
each other, rejoice in hope together, persevere
in tribulation together, be the vote of the prayer together, contribute to the needs of the saints together.
Listen, to sit back and just watch it happen is not an acceptable response to God's grace.
Well, I just like the key to myself, preacher.
Well, I don't know if I trust the church in my money anyway.
Well, I don't think the church should be a business.
Allow me to respond to some of these ungodly responses.
First off, You don't get to keep to yourself in a family of God.
See, we need your gifts and abilities for the sake of the gospel ministry.
Did I did you just hear me?
I'm not saying you can't be replaced because I'm replaceable.
You understand what I'm saying?
If I refuse to stand up here and preach?
somebody will stand up here and preach.
I just desire it to be me.
Amen?
Because that's how God has gifted me and called me.
But I'm just telling you right now, it's not that it's not that
God needs you to where like no one else can do it.
What I'm saying is the grace that you've been given, the gift that you've been given.
Listen, hey, it is to be used for his glory.
Quit living for self and be a part of what God is doing.
Second, if you were at a church where you don't trust how they strew the money, find another church where you can.
I couldn't imagine giving my tithe to a church and think, man, I hope they do good things with this.
That's ridiculous.
And if you always sin and not trust the church and it's not the church's
fault, then it's probably your heart posture's fault.
By the way, if you did more than just give a check
and you were actually involved, you might be able to visually see what that contribution is going towards.
In other words, when you're on a stewardship team, right?
And a kid needs sponsoring.
You might be able to physically see that contribution come to
life when a kid gives his life to Christ by being in the Iwana program.
You understand what I'm saying there?
Listen, but if you sit back and you just give your check and
you give your money and say, oh, I'm a good old Christian, listen, no wonder you're bitter.
No wonder you're sour.
You're not seeing what God is doing with it.
Y'all with me this morning.
Listen, you can't fire me until I'm done with Romans.
And we've got a long way to go.
By the time we get there, you'll have change your mind 3 or 4 times.
So third,
Well, I don't think a church should be a business.
We wouldn't claim that for any other part of our life.
In every other part of our life, we are pursuing success and bettering our situation, or at least we hopefully are.
Amen?
Why not for the house of God?
Guys, I want everything that we do to be done in excellence.
Why not for the magnification of the ministry here at Cedar Grove?
A church is not inherently a business?
Absolutely not, but a well-run and well-mannished church is a high impact ministry in a community.
If everything's chaos here,
Listen, if we allow things to be chaotic here, we're not stewarding what God has given us.
And on top of my responses to those selfish thoughts, may I encourage you
with scripture, James 410 says this, humble yourself in
the presence of the Lord, and he will exalt you.
Amen?
Let me tell you, let me tell you in my translation.
Get over yourself.
Be a part of something.
May we hear at Cedar Grove, never forget what God says about giving in 2nd Corinthians 9, verse 6 and 7.
Now this I say, he who sows sparingly will also reap sparingly.
And he who sows bountifully will also reap bountifully.
Each one must do just as he purposed in his heart,
not grudgingly or under compulsion, for God loves a cheerful giver.
That word bountifully literally means, listen, we
have an idea of what it means, but it means blessing and praise.
refers to speech that invokes blessing or the positive circumstance associated with blessing.
Don't miss the beauty of this.
We give out of blessing and praise to the Lord.
And if we are determined to do so, we must do so,
not because we have to, but because we happily choose to.
That's why when we take up the tithe and offering, we always try to
say, this is an extension of our worship to the Lord.
You know what this tells me?
One of the most joyful parts of our gatherings together ought to be when we take up our ties and offerings.
Why?
Because we know that when we sow bountifully, we will reap bountifully.
By the way, I want everyone just to look around for a second.
We have almost 200 people here this morning.
That's a lot.
That's a lot, okay?
Someone say, hey man, get excited about God working.
I need my hanky.
I'm starting to sweat.
But listen, hey.
What you are, what you are partaking
in this morning, is something that has been worked for.
contributed to and prayed for way before this Sunday.
Those seats that we were able to bring out more and more of.
This poor section over here.
I know the TV is out and this is the biggest section we have.
It's okay.
But the seats that we added over here,
Listen, hey, we were able to purchase those without any problem.
No problem at all.
It wasn't a question.
It wasn't -oh, like if we do this, can we do this?
Can we do it?
no, no.
was like, you know what, God, you bless us.
Let's go buy 200 shares.
Listen, when we do the things that we're doing, like when we fix this TV, we're going to fix a lot of other things too.
You know what?
Because we can.
Guys listen, that's a blessing.
That's a gift from God right there.
I want the best of the best because we serve the best of the best.
The one and only true God.
Again, if we had this correct heart posture,
our money would never be a problem or hindrance here at Cedar
Grove, our budget would not serve to limit, but rather it would serve to the ministry.
Now, this command is connected with the next command.
Okay?
We're going to get off that for a second.
You can now breathe.
contributing to the needs of the saints.
We also see in verse 13, look at it.
Practicing hospitality.
See, hospitality continues in the meaning of sharing with others material and tangible things.
The Greek term literally means practical kindness
paid especially to strangers, often in the sharing of food and drink, lodging, and provision.
That's what hospitality is.
Guys, you know why?
Listen, if you knew, you're going to find that you might see me, I'll meet with you, right?
And then I'll get your name.
Hopefully I remember your name.
All right?
I'm not very good with names.
I'm trying to get better with names.
But what I'll do, if you pay attention, I'm going to start going to other people that go here.
And I'm going to say, hey, you may not have noticed.
Well, I don't know why I'm What's up, bro?
You may not have noticed, but that person over there, they're new.
Go see them.
Go love on them.
And listen, I'm not trying to force the envelope, but if you don't, I'm going to be very mad.
No, but seriously, you go, why?
Because we want to be hospitable.
But see, hospitality in this command is not just saying hi and how you doing it and everything.
Hospitality is paying attention to the needs.
Hospitality is listening to what they say.
Hospitality is making sure that if there is a need that you can contribute to.
If there's a need that you can help in.
If there's something or a provision that you can share in, you don't overlook it, we made it.
Now, I'm not saying that we have to, you know, be abused or taken advantage of.
But what I'm saying is we are to be open to others as God has blessed us.
This does not mean, again, to be taken advantage, but
God gives us discernment in the Holy Spirit to help us know when and how, but there must be a win and how in our life.
People say all the time.
People get onto me.
I can't tell you how many times I've been yelled at on the phone about, hey, I need to have a knee.
Can you meet?
I said, we don't, you know, hey, you know what?
This is what I usually say.
Hey, meet me at church.
If it's like, you know, close to Sunday.
I'll say Sunday, close to Wednesday.
I say Wednesday.
You come to church, and we'll have a conversation.
We'll see what we can do for you.
You know what to do?
Click.
Help me help you.
But understand that every blessing that I have to help with has come from Jesus.
And in other words, listen, everything that we do here is yes
to help and contribute, but it doesn't mean that we just throw our money at everyone.
It doesn't mean that we just, you know, go out on our way on people that are taking advantage.
What it means is that we are just given to hospitality.
There was a win and where.
Let's continue in our word study here.
That word practice was going to give us some more clarity. is
a word that is not get its due diligence in the English language.
That when Paul uses this word in this verse, it literally means to strive to.
To do something with an intense effort to a goal.
In other words, we are commanded to strive to.
That is to pursue friendliness to others even strangers.
There's anything missing in the church today.
It's this.
We live such separate lives.
We live completely closed off to the outside world.
And we wonder why we have a hard time seeing the fruit of our ministry labor.
We wonder why people seem to not receive the good news of the gospel as openly as we think they should.
is because our society has separated us.
Our culture has separated us.
We're all living for number one.
We're all living for our own family.
We're all doing this, we're all doing that.
We have our schedules.
We have our routines, we have this, we have that, and we don't have time for anyone else.
Listen, I'm standing before you as a dad of three.
In other words, I understand the routine.
I understand ballet.
I understand T-ball.
I understand extracurriculus.
I understand family dinners.
I understand the fact that when you get a Thursday night to yourself and just your family, you want to take advantage of that.
But we're still commanded to pursue, to strive.
to be hospitable.
Again, I'm not unaware that there are dangers out there.
I'm not saying live recklessly and without common sense, but do not allow the
world we live in to be used in a justification for a disobedient life.
There was one time we were going and we were doing door-to-door way back when, I think 2017 or 18.
And we were going door to door and I had a man come to me and they made it very clear.
They said, they said, I'm not going door to door.
And now back then I was a lot rougher around the edges than I am now.
Okay, I'm a lot kinder now than I was back then.
And I looked at that dude.
I said, well, you mean you're not going door to door?
He goes, well, that's just dangerous.
I said, excuse me, what, bro?
He said, well, someone can take a bat and beat your head in.
I'm like, well, good gracious, bro.
Where do you think we're going?
We're just going around the neighborhood.
Say, well, I'm not going because it's too dangerous.
Can I tell you something?
That's an excuse.
Amen?
Y'all probably think the same thing.
Y'all think that every time you go to your house, you get your head beating with a bat?
What's wrong with y'all?
What world y'all living in?
What I'm trying to say is we can't let the world we live.
Listen, the world we live in is gonna get worse.
Therefore, they need the world needs the church to be
the church more and more, to be obedient to his commands more than we even are now.
We want to continue to light this can.
Why?
Because there's so much darkness around us.
But here's a sad reality.
Biblical Christianity seems radical because
we have replaced it with a religion of convenience and self-worship.
We have become comfortable in our own way.
We have traded community for screen.
Rather than a hug and a prayer, our connections are now like a now a like and a share of a post.
And in doing so, I believe we have quenched the Holy Spirit.
We take seeing someone's picture online to being connected with them.
Listen, church, that's not it.
That's not how we're called to be.
So where does this find you this morning?
As we come to a close, how do you see your generous contributions of your own tangible blessings?
How do you view them?
You live life with a clenched fist.
You live life in such a way that you have to have every safe
or every single thing that you give, where it goes and how it goes.
And if you don't like it, then well, well, I don't like chairs, so I'm not giving to the offering for chairs.
Well, I mean, mercy.
We can fit more people in here.
Amen?
I don't give a rip.
Listen, if we could fit more people in lazy boys, we'd invest in lazy boys.
That's what we do.
I mean, goodness gracious.
How do you see contributing to these of the saints?
Are you still living in this idea that you can pick and choose?
that we can somehow distort what scripture is clear about, how we become so
high and mighty that we know better than God.
Guys, we got to stop listening to social media theologians.
and read the Bible.
Anyone that gives you theology that
takes you further from the church and further from obedience in God is a false prophet.
They are a wolf in sheep's clothing.
And people are flocking to them.
You strive to be hospitable towards others.
And guys, I listen, I live in the same world you do.
I got to sign in my house.
Hey, you're welcome, but leave by nine.
That's just, my wife put it up.
didn't put it up.
should put it up.
But we're so closed off.
I literally, I was thinking the other day, just to let you know that I think about this like I'm asking you to think about it.
I literally thought in my mind, man, how do I connect with my people outside of Sunday?
Like, I can't eat dinner every night with all of them because, I mean, it's just impossible.
Do I do a once a month dinner?
How do I pick which family to do it?
Is it gonna cause jealousy?
How do, what?
Here's the here's the thing.
It's not necessarily how we do it.
Is just if we are actually striving to do it.
In other words, if you try to do something, guess what?
You'll figure it out.
Amen?
By the way, these kind of contributions have an eternal character to them.
Whereas most contributions are temporary.
It's kind of like this.
Through the ups and downs, notice it wasn't a contingency on the disciples of what was going on in their life.
They were just determined.
See, I have I have some retirement accounts that I pay in every single month.
I, I, you know, I want, I want that that dream of having a 1000000 bucks at 60.
You know what I'm saying?
that would be really cool.
If you think that's ungodly, then, you know, give me your money.
I don't know, tell you.
I mean, you know what I'm saying?
I'll have a million, you won't.
don't know.
But I do.
I put it in a Roth, I do all the things, everything everyone says to do, I try to do.
We may have a bad month.
Guess what I still do.
I still contribute.
We may have a really good month.
Guess what I do?
I still contribute.
Why?
Because I know that I'm playing a long game.
And I know that it doesn't matter where the market is, whether it's high, whether it's
low, whether it's right here, whether it's stagnant, whether it's, you know, whatever it is.
I'm gonna contribute.
Guys, listen, spiritually, whether you're on a high?
whether you're on a low, whether things are going really good, or really bad.
We are to contribute.
I'm not just talking about money here.
I'm talking about our hospitality.
I'm talking about a devotion to each other.
Guys, listen, we contribute to the needs of the saints.
There was a time when we went really, really high with the
crowd and we were about to break the 200 mark, which is like the legendary
mark for churches, our size, and once you break the 200, and it's like, you've made it.
God humbled us and Went down like crazy.
We were like meeting Sunday morning, there would be 80 something people here.
And let me just tell you something.
I know that you think, well, it's not about the amount of the crowd.
Okay, you get up here then.
Like, it's nice when people show up.
Amen?
It's nice.
But you know what we did?
We just kept on contributing.
We just kept on doing.
We kept on loving on these kids.
We kept on loving on these families.
We kept on striving and pursuing.
I kept on preaching.
Listen, my study now doesn't look any different in my study then.
Why?
Because it's eternal contributions.
It has eternal character to it.
That's the mindset we got to have.
See, the girl, maybe we heed God's word and as we come to a kind of like a break in the text.
Look at Romans 12, verse 9 to 13 will be done.
Let love be without hypocrisy.
Abhor what is evil.
That means separate yourself from what is evil.
Dance yourself.
Cling to what is good.
Be devoted to one another in brotherly love, give preference to one another in honor.
Not lagging behind in diligence, fervent in spirit,
serving the Lord, rejoicing in hope, persevering in tribulation, devoted
the prayer, contributing to the needs of the saints, practicing hospitality.
Let us be that.
But has Ben Oz closed over this place?